Guide to the Robert Raymo Papers MC.214
New York University Archives
Robert Raymo Papers
1926-2008
1953-2008
New York University Archives
Raymo, Robert R.
MC.214
13.25 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 9 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 2 flat boxes, and 2 custom boxes
Robert Raymo was an internationally renowned scholar of medieval English literature who spent the majority of his academic career at New York University. Professor Raymo chaired NYU's English Department (1969-1972) and Dramatic Literature Department (1969-1974) and served as the founding director of NYU's Medieval and Renaissance Studies Program. He also served as dean of NYU's Graduate School of Arts and Science from 1974 to 1979. His collection consists of scholarly books and book chapters Raymo either authored or edited, as well as numerous bibliographic and research materials Professor Raymo kept throughout his academic career. His papers also include correspondence with prominent writers and scholars, administrative reports and texts related to his service at NYU, and numerous inscribed and annotated books and offprints pertaining to his involvement in medieval literature circles.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Arrangement
The collection was kept in its original order arranged in six series:
I. Publications and Related Bound Materials
II. Research Materials
III. Administrative Papers
IV. Personal Papers
V. Memorabilia
VI. Annotated Texts and Inscribed Volumes
Biographical Note
Robert Raymo (1925-2009), a scholar of medieval English literature, served the majority of his academic career at New York University. He arrived at the University in 1964 as a professor of English and was named professor emeritus in 2002. Raymo chaired NYU's English Department (1969-1972) and Dramatic Literature Department (1969-1974) and served as the founding director of NYU's Medieval and Renaissance Studies Program. He also served as dean of NYU's Graduate School of Arts and Science from 1974 to 1979.
Born in Pelham Manor on January 23, 1925, Raymo earned a B.A. at Fordham University in 1945. He received a scholarship from the American Academy of Classical Studies in Rome and a grant in aid from Columbia University to continue his studies at the graduate level. He received an M.A. in English from Columbia University in 1947 and used his two consecutive Fulbright Awards (1949-1957) for research to earn a doctorate at Cambridge University in 1953 in medieval and modern languages. He began his academic career in 1953 when he was appointed an instructor of English at the University of California at Los Angeles. Two years later, UCLA appointed him assistant professor of English, a position he held until 1957, when he joined the faculty at Rutgers University. By 1960 Raymo attained a full professorship at Rutgers, leaving 4 years later (1964) to join the NYU English faculty at the Graduate School of Arts and Science. In 1964 he also received the Lindback Foundation Award for Excellence and Distinguished Teaching and the Rutgers University Alumni Distinguished Teacher Award.
Raymo's administrative career with NYU encompasses his responsibilities as Head of the All-University Department of English, a post that discontinued in 1972 as a result of sale of the University Heights Campus in the Bronx. In 1969 he was named Chairman of the Department of English at Washington Square College, a position he retained with the merger of NYU's entire undergraduate and graduate faculty at the Washington Square Campus in 1973. He also served as a member of NYU's University Senate from 1969-1972, representing the interests of Washington Square College. From 1971 to 1973, he sat on the Budget Committee and advised the Chancellor on University budgetary policy. For several months he also served as member of the Committee on the Financial Emergency where he reviewed and commented on the 1972 Report of the Task Force, offering independent suggestions to improve the University's financial situation.
As a linguist and manuscript editor, Raymo focused his academic pursuits on medieval English literature of the 14th and 15th centuries and on works of Chaucer. As a book collector, he held memberships at both the Grolier Club, where he curated an exhibit of his collection commemorating the 600th anniversary of Chaucer's death, and the Lotos Club. During the last years of his life, he worked on compiling a comprehensive bibliography of Chaucer editions from 1447 to the present, based largely on his private collection. Raymo died on July 16, 2009 of cancer at New York City's Calvary Hospital.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was transferred to the University Archives by Professor Raymo's wife, Judith Raymo, in 2010. Accretions to the collection were donated in July 2021 and November 2022. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 10.017, 2021.031, and 2022.092, respectively.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes a number of publications that Raymo authored, contributed to, or edited, as well as multiple bibliographical texts relating to "Manuscripts of Religious and Philosophical Instruction," his chapter in Manual of Writings in Middle English vol. 7 (1986). His other publications include: two manuscript copies of his 1953 dissertation, The Mirror for Fools By Nigel de Longchamps. A Translation into English with an Introduction and Commentary; Speculum Stultorum, ed. John H. Mozley and Robert R. Raymo (Berkeley, 1960) – a critical edition of the Latin text; and A Mirror for Fools: The Book of Burnel the Ass, trans. John H. Mozley – English translation, (2 hardcover copies (Oxford, 1961) and 1 softcover (University of Notre Dame Press, 1963)).
Also included are annotated secondary material, notes, and photocopies of scholarly articles relating to Raymo's work on The Mirror for Fools/Speculum Stultorum (1953 – 1963), "Middle English Works of Religious and Philosophical Instruction" (1986), The Mirroure of the Worlde (2003), and "Sources and Analogues of the General Prologue," in Sources and Analogues of the Canterbury Tales, Vol. 2 (2005). For his authoritative chapter "Middle English Works of Religious and Philosophical Instruction" in A Manual of the Writings in Middle English, 1050-1100, Vol. 7 (1986), Raymo compiled 1800 bibliographic entries gleaned from his research in approximately 250 western European and American libraries. He recorded many of his bibliographic findings on the index cards and notebooks contained within this series.
Materials include correspondence, and notes and articles relating to the John Donne Colloquium Raymo conducted at the Grolier Club, award certificates and scholarship letters he received over the course of his career, various offprints signed by authors, a published schedule of the 38th International Congress on Medieval Studies listing two sessions honoring Professor Raymo, a pewter plate celebrating the 90th Anniversary of NYU's Graduate School of Arts and Science, and annotated texts and books inscribed to Raymo. As a bibliophile and book collector, he specialized in the works of Chaucer and curated an exhibition of his collection at the Grolier Club (of which he was a longtime member) in 2000 to commemorate the 600th anniversary of Chaucer's death. This series reflects his affinity for book collecting, and includes a number of annotated texts and inscribed books and offprints Raymo acquired through his various associations in medieval scholarship circles, spanning the years 1928 – 2007.
Correspondence.; Administrative reports.; Awards; Bibliographies; Manuscripts for publication.; Manuscripts; English literature -- Middle English, 1100-1500 -- History and criticism -- Addresses, essays, lectures; Brée, Germaine -- Correspondence; Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400 -- History -- Sources; Bellow, Saul -- Correspondence; MacDiarmid, Hugh, 1892-1978 -- Correspondence; Doyle, A. I. (Anthony Ian), 1925- -- Correspondence; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science; Coghill, Rhoda, 1903-2000 -- Correspondence; Lewis, R. W. B. (Richard Warrington Baldwin), 1917-2002 -- Correspondence; Lipset, Seymour Martin -- Correspondence; Canaday, John, 1907-1985 -- Correspondence; Van den Haag, Ernest. -- Correspondence; New York University -- Faculty -- History; New York University -- Administration -- History; Lotos Club (New York, N.Y.); Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400 -- Canterbury tales; Wireker, Nigellus, approximately 1130-approximately 1200 -- Speculum stultorum -- English; Donne, John, 1572-1631; Grolier Club
- Series I. Publications and Related Bound Materials, 1926 - 1967
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes a number of publications that Raymo authored, contributed to, or edited, as well as multiple bibliographical texts relating to "Manuscripts of Religious and Philosophical Instruction," his chapter in Manual of Writings in Middle English vol. 7 (1986). His other publications include: two manuscript copies of his 1953 dissertation, The Mirror for Fools By Nigel de Longchamps. A Translation into English with an Introduction and Commentary; Speculum Stultorum, ed. John H. Mozley and Robert R. Raymo (Berkeley, 1960) – a critical edition of the Latin text; and A Mirror for Fools: The Book of Burnel the Ass, trans. John H. Mozley – English translation, (2 hardcover copies (Oxford, 1961) and 1 softcover (University of Notre Dame Press, 1963)).
  - Subseries IA: Mirror of Fools/Speculum Stultorum (1960)
    - Dissertation: The Mirror for Fools By Nigel de Longchamps. A Translation into English with an Introduction and Commentary, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Mirror of Fools By Nigel de Longchamps. A Translation by Robert Raymo, Vol. 2, annotated Ph.D. dissertation., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Nigellus De Longchamp Dit Wireker, Universite libre de Bruxelles. Travaux de la Faculte de philosophie et lettres,t. 16, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nigel de Longchamps Speculum Stultorum, Edited by J.H. Mozley and R. R. Raymo. (2 copies), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A Mirror for Fools: The Book of Burnel the Ass by Nigel Longchamp. Translated from the Latin with Introduction and Notes by J. H. Mozley with Illustrations by Eve Graham. Hardcover with dust jacket ( Basil Blackwell, 1961) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A Mirror for Fools: The Book of Burnel the Ass by Nigel Longchamp. Translated from the Latin with Introduction and Notes by J. H. Mozley with Illustrations by Eve Graham. Softcover (University of Notre Dame Press, 1963); with bookplate of P. E. Beichner (author of Preface) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - A Syllabus of Comparative Literature, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IB. "Manuscripts of Religious and Philosophical Instruction," (edited by Robert Raymo) in Manual of Writings in Middle English vol. 7 (1986)., 1926 - 1955
    - Lists of manuscripts formerly in Peterborough Abbey Library, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - A Bibliography of Fifteenth Century Literature, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Medieval Texts and Their First Appearance in Print, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Transactions of the Cambridge Bibliographical Society, (2 copies, for the years 1949 and 1950), 1949 - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - British Museum: The Catalogues of the Manuscript Collections, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Traditio: Studies in Ancient and Medieval History, Thought and Religion, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. Research Materials, 1967 - 2005
  Series II includes annotated secondary material, notes, and photocopies of scholarly articles relating to Raymo's work on The Mirror for Fools/Speculum Stultorum (1953 – 1963), "Middle English Works of Religious and Philosophical Instruction" (1986), The Mirroure of the Worlde (2003), and "Sources and Analogues of the General Prologue," in Sources and Analogues of the Canterbury Tales, Vol. 2 (2005). For his authoritative chapter "Middle English Works of Religious and Philosophical Instruction" in A Manual of the Writings in Middle English, 1050-1100, Vol. 7 (1986), Raymo compiled 1800 bibliographic entries gleaned from his research in approximately 250 western European and American libraries. He recorded many of his bibliographic findings on the index cards and notebooks contained within this series.
  - Subseries IIA. Research for Mirror of Fools/Speculum Stultorum
    - Additional MSS of Speculum, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Recent Additions on Speculum Stultorum and Satire – Horace, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Recent Additions on Speculum Stultorum and Satire – Satire References, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IIB. Research for "Manuscripts of Religious and Philosophical Instruction," (edited by Robert Raymo) in Manual of Writings in Middle English vol. 7 (1986).
    - List of Manuals and Miscellany #1-3, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cambridge – Eta to Zeta and #3, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Oxford, Edinburgh, London (BM), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - London & Oxford – Alpha & Epsilon [Manuals of confession in French], undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Notes on confessional manuals, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Translations – Misc., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Verse Tracts on the Sins, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Drury's Tractatus de Modo Confitendi, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Middle English Version of Prone & Profitable Table of Feythe, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Robbins' Supplement, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Penitential Literature, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - ALS from Nancy Regalado, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Catalogue of Manuscripts for Manual – Index Cards, undated (Box 6)
    - Catalogue of Manuscripts for Manual - Index Cards (continued), undated (Box 7)
  - Subseries IIC. Research for The Mirroure of the Worlde (2003)
    - Scrope's will (search for) and Sir John Falstof (stepfather and soldier in War of Roses), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Sir Stephen Scrope – translator of Mirroure of the Worlde, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Authorship – Mirroure and other works, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Scrope's Replycaciones and Addits, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Richard II's court culture – articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Mirroure-addenda, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Translation of Latin MS of Martin of Tours, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 14th and 15th Century England – Articles and Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence and Reviews - Mirroure, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - J'ai tout perdu – notes and translations, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Mirroure – Glossary draft (ca. 500 pages), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - MSS (microfiche) - Humbert (Sermons and status) (Oversized), undated (Box 5)
    - MSS (microfiche) - Gilbert de Tournay (Oversized), undated (Box 5)
  - Subseries IID. Research for "Sources and Analogues of the General Prologue," in SOURCES AND ANALOGUES OF THE CANTERBURY TALES, VOL. 2 (2005)
    - Clerk, undated (Box 2, Folder 27, Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Cook, undated (Box 2, Folder 28, Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Franklin, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Friar, undated (Box 2, Folder 29, Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Guildsmen, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Knight, undated (Box 2, Folder 31, Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Manciple, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Merchant, undated (Box 2, Folder 33, Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Miller, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Monk, undated (Box 3, Folder 2, Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Nun's Priest, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Pardoner, undated (Box 3, Folder 4, Box 9)
    - Parson, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Physician, undated (Box 3, Folder 5, Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Plowman, undated (Box 3, Folder 6, Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Prioress, undated (Box 3, Folder 7, Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Reeve, undated (Box 3, Folder 8, Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Sergeant at Law, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Shipman, undated (Box 3, Folder 10, Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Squire, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Squire/Yeoman, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Summoner, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Wife of Bath, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Yeoman, undated (Box 3, Folder 14, Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Portraits – General, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Date of General Prologue, circa 1950s-2008 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Manuscript Drafts, 1990-2008 (Box 10, Folder 1-7, Box 11, Folder 1-3)
    - Chaucer Bibliography, circa 1950s-2008 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Chaucer -- General, circa 1950s-2008 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Langland and Chaucer, circa 1950s-2008 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Bibliographic Research, circa 1990s-2009 (Box 16, Folder 1-10, Box 17, Folder 1-9, Box 18, Folder 1-3)
    - The Book of Daun Burnel the Ass (Nigellus Wireker), 1959 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Notebook, circa 1990s-2009 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Index Cards, circa 1990s-2009 (Box 18, Folder 6-7)
  - Subseries IIE. General Middle English Research
    This series consists of handwritten notes and photocopies of journal articles concerning Medieval and Renaissance literature and poetry.
    - Articles, Notes, circa 1950s-2008 (Box 12, Folder 1-13, Box 13, Folder 1-7, Box 14, Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Notebooks, circa 1950s-2008 (Box 15, Folder 2-4)
- Series III. Administrative Papers, 1966 - 2002
  Series III encompasses Raymo's administrative responsibilities at NYU as Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science and thereafter, and includes reports he authored on undergraduate and graduate education at the university, as well as well as books on graduate education.
  - Appointment as Dean & Deans Annual Reports., 1975 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - C.P. Snow Address, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Task Force on Quality of CAS, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The Doctorate at NYU", 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Curriculum Vitae and professional Statement, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - An Assessment of Quality in Graduate Education (Book)., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - A Century of Doctorates (Book), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The State of Graduate Education (Book), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series IV. Personal Papers, 1932 - 2008
  Series IV consists of correspondence, and notes and articles relating to the John Donne Colloquium Raymo conducted at the Grolier Club, as well as award certificates and scholarship letters he received over the course of his career.
  - Subseries IVA. Correspondence, 1957 - 1991
    - Saul Bellow (5/10/74), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Germaine Bree (5/29/76), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Jane E. (12/7/78), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Terri Schultz (7/7/78), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Seymour Lipset (2/7/74), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Ernest van den Haag (2/10/61), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - John Canaday (1/19/61) (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - John Gassner (1/28/61), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hugh MacDiarmind aka Christopher Grieve (8/13/60), 1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Rhoda Coghill (10-6-60), 1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - A. I. Doyle (11/5/91), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Richard W. B. Lewis (2/7/57), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Richard W. B. Lewis (2/21/57) – postcard, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - N. Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie (1/29/80), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - N. Emmanuel le Roy Ladurie (3/28/80), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Emmanuel Le Roy Lladurie (6/5/80), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Subseries IVB. John Donne Colloquium – Notes and Articles, 2008
    - Notes on John Donne, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Poems – A reading of Donne, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Chronology and Illustrations, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous Reviews and Articles, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "John Donne's Marriage Letters...", 2005 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Subseries IVC. Awards and Scholarships
    - Childhood Effects, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Fulbright Award letters, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Lindback Excellence in Teaching Award – Rutgers, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fordham University Distinguished Alumni Award (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Festschrift – Satura edited by R.E. Sternglantz and N. Reale (on shelf in Library) (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Series V. Memorabilia
  Series V includes various offprints signed by authors, a published schedule of the 38th International Congress on Medieval Studies listing two sessions honoring Professor Raymo, and a pewter plate celebrating the 90th Anniversary of NYU's Graduate School of Arts and Science.
  - Offprints Signed by Authors, 1947-1986 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - 38th International Congress on Medieval Studies, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Pewter GSAS 90th Anniversary Plate (Box 8)
- Series VI. Annotated Texts and Inscribed Volumes
  Series VI includes annotated texts and books inscribed to Raymo. As a bibliophile and book collector, he specialized in the works of Chaucer and curated an exhibition of his collection at the Grolier Club (of which he was a longtime member) in 2000 to commemorate the 600th anniversary of Chaucer's death. This series reflects his affinity for book collecting, and includes a number of annotated texts and inscribed books and offprints Raymo acquired through his various associations in medieval scholarship circles, spanning the years 1928 – 2007. The dates presented in Series V. represent the books' copyright dates. Inscribed/signed books have the date of inscription on the folder title.
  - An Introduction to Bibliography (Inscribed, 8/1990), 1928 (Box 4)
  - Beowulf and Epic Tradition, 1928 (Box 4)
  - Beowulf, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Medieval Libraries of Great Britain, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Medieval English Verse and Prose, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Medieval English Verse and Prose, 1948 (Box 4)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Fragile Spine.
  - Traditio: Studies in Ancient and Medieval History, Thought and Religion, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Virgil's The Aeneid, 1958 (Box 4)
  - John Gower: Moral Philosopher and Friend of Chaucer, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Lydgate Poems, 1966 (Box 4)
  - English Medieval Graffiti (Inscribed, 1975), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Morte Arthure (Annotated Teaching Text), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Sir Gawain and the Green Knight, 1968 (Box 4)
  - The Kingis Quair of James Stewart, 1973 (Box 4)
  - A Check-List of Middle English Prose Writings of Spiritual Guidance, 1974 (Box 4)
  - The Canon of Sir Thomas Wyatt's Poetry, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Sir Gawan and the Green Knight, 1975 (Box 4)
  - The Divine Comedy of Dante Aligheri: Inferno, 1982 (Box 4)
  - The Divine Comedy of Dante Aligheri: Purgatorio, 1984 (Box 4)
  - The Oxford Book of Late Medieval Verse and Prose, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Augustine, 1986 (Box 4)
  - The Divine Comedy of Dante Aligheri: Paradiso, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Warrenpoint, 1990 (Box 4)
  - The Riverside Chaucer (Raymo's annotated teaching text)., 1987 (Box 4)
    Taped at the spine – Raymo removed the spine initially so that he could bring select pages of the text to class.
  - Piers Plowman, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Saint Augustine Confessions, 1992 (Box 4)
  - The Reinvention of Love, 1993 (Box 4)
  - 38th International Congress on Medieval Studies, 2003 (Box 4)
  - An Evening Celebrating the Poetry of John Keats (Grolier Club), 2007 (Box 4)
  - Langland Piers Plowman Books I – VII, (2 copies), undated (Box 4)
  - James I of Scotland: The Kingis Quair, undated (Box 4)